What's happening to the climate?
ما يحدث للمناخ؟
It is unbelievably bad.
شئ مؤسف لا يصدق
This is, obviously, that famous view now of the Arctic,
هذا، بطبيعة الحال، المشهد المشهور للقطب الشمالي
which is likely to be gone at this point
الذي من المرجح أنه أنتهى الى هذا الحد
in the next three or four or five years. Very, very, very scary.
السنوات الثلاث أو الأربع أو الخمس القادمة. مخيفة جداً جداً جداً
So we all look at what we can do.
لذا فقد بحثنا ما يمكننا فعله
And when you look at the worldwide sources of CO2,
وعندما ننظر الى مصادر ثاني أكسيد الكربون عالمياً
52 percent are tied to buildings.
52 في المائة منها منسوبة للمباني
Only nine percent is passenger cars, interestingly enough.
تسعة في المائة منها فقط من السيارات، مثير للإهتمام
So we ran off to a sushi bar.
لذا هرعنا الى مطعم للسوشي
And at that sushi bar we came up with a great idea.
وفي المطعم توصلنا الى هذه الفكرة العظيمة
And it was something called EcoRock.
وكان شيئاً أسميناه إيكو روك
And we said we could redesign the 115-year-old
وقلنا أننا يمكن أن نعيد تصميم الجبس ذا 115 عام
gypsum drywall process that generates
التي تنتج
20 billion pounds of CO2 a year.
20 بليون رطلا من ثاني أكسيد الكربون سنوياً
So it was a big idea. We wanted to reduce that by 80 percent,
أذن كانت فكرة هائلة. أردنا تقليل الإنبعاث ب 80 في المائة
which is exactly what we've done.
الشئ الذي نفذناه تماماً
We started R&amp;D in 2006.
بدأنا بحوث وتطوير عام 2006
Decided to use recycled content from cement
قررنا إستخدام محتويات مدوّرة من الأسمنت
and steel manufacturing.
والصلب التحويلي
There is the inside of our lab. We haven't shown this before.
هنا من داخل المختبر. لم نعرض هذا من قبل
But our people had to do some 5,000
لكن باحثينا أضطروا لخلط 5000
different mixes to get this right, to hit our targets.
مركبات مختلفة للوصول للنتيجة، والهدف المنشود
And they worked absolutely very, very, very hard.
وعملوا بجدية منقطعة النظير
So then we went forward and built our production line in China.
لذا مضينا قدماً وبنينا خط إنتاجنا في الصين
We don't build this production equipment any longer in the U.S., unfortunately.
لم نعد نبني آلالات الإنتاج هذه في الولايات المتحدة. بكل أسف
We did the line install over the summer.
قمنا بتركيب خط الإنتاج خلال الصيف
We started right there, with absolutely nothing.
بدأنا من هناك، من لا شئ
You're seeing for the first time, a brand new drywall production line,
تشاهدون ولأول مرة، خط إنتاج حوائط جافة جديد كليا
not made using gypsum at all.
لم يصنع بتاتاً بإستخدام الجبس
That's the finished production line there.
تبدو نهاية خط الإنتاج هناك
We got our first panel out on December third.
حصلنا على أول إنتاج في الثالث من ديسمبر
That is the slurry being poured onto paper, basically. That's the line running.
هذا هو الطين المسال الى الورق أساسا. وهناك الخط يعمل
The exciting thing is, look at the faces of the people.
الشئ المثير هو، أنظروا لوجوه الناس
These are people who worked this project for two to three years.
هؤلاء هم من عملوا في هذا المشروع لمدة سنتين الى ثلاثة
And they are so excited. That's the first board off the line.
وهم متشوقون للغاية. ذاك أول فريق خارج الخط
Our Vice President of Operation kissing the board. Obviously very, very excited.
نائب رئيس العمليات يقبّل اللوحة. بطبيعة الحال متشوق جداً جداً
But this has a huge, huge impact on the environment.
لكن لهذا تأثير ضخم جداً على بيئتنا
We signed the first panel just a few weeks after that, had a great signing ceremony,
وقّعنا أول لوحة لنا بعد أسابيع قليلة من ذلك، وسط إحتفال عظيم
leading to people hopefully using these products across the world.
على أمل أن نقود الناس لإستخدام هذه المنتجات حول العالم
And we've got Cradle-to-Cradle Gold on this thing.
وحصلنا على شهادة Cradle to Cradle Gold في هذا الشئ
We happened to win, just recently, the Green Product of the Year
حصل أن فزنا، مؤخراً على المنتج الأخضر للعام
for "The Re-Invention of Drywall," from Popular Science.
ل " إعادة إختراع الحائط الجاف،" من مجلة العلوم المبسّطة
Thank you. Thank you.
شكراً لكم، شكراً لكم
So here is what we learned: 8,000 gallons of gas
أذن هذا ما تعلمناه. 8000 جالون من الغاز
equivalent to build one house.
تكافئ بناء بيت واحد
You probably had no idea. It's like driving around the world six times.
ربما ليس لديكم فكرة. أنها مثل قيادة السيارة حول العالم ست مرات
We must change everything.
يجب أن نغيّر كل شئ
Look around the room: chairs, wood,
أنظر حول الغرفة، الكراسي، الخشب
everything around us has to change or we're not going to lick this problem.
كل شئ حولنا يجب أن يتغير أو أننا لن نقدر على إمتصاص هذه المشكلة
Don't listen to the people who say you can't do this, because anyone can.
لا تستمعوا الى الناس الذين يعجزونكم، لأن كل شئ يستطيع
And these job losses, we can fix them with green-collar jobs.
وهذه الخسائر في الوظائف، يمكننا إستبدالها بوظائف خضراء
We've got four plants. We're building this stuff around the country.
حصلنا على أربع مصانع. نصنع هذه الأشياء في كل البلد
We're going as fast as we can.
نمضي بأسرع ما نستطيع
Two and a half million cars worth of gypsum,
ما يعادل قيمة أثنان ونصف مليون سيارة من الجبس
you know, CO2 generated. Right?
تعرفون، إنبعاث ثاني أكسيد الكربون، صحيح؟
So what will you do? I'll tell you what I did and why I did it. And I know my time's up.
أذن ماذا سنفعل؟ سأخبركم ماذا فعلت ولماذا فعلته. وأعرف أن زمني أنتهى
Those are my kids, Natalie and David.
هؤلاء أبنائي، ناتالي وديفيد
When they have their kids, 2050,
عندما يكون لديهم أطفال عام 2050
they'd better look back at Grandpa and say,
سينظروا على جدهم ويقولوا
"Hey, you gave it a good shot. You did the best you could
هاى، لقد فعلت جيداً. فعلت أحسن ما أستطعت
with the team that you had."
مع الفريق المصاحب لك
So my hope is that when you leave TED,
لذا فأملي أنكم عندما تغادرون TED
you will look at reducing your carbon footprint
ستبحثوا في تقليل إنبعاث الكربون
in however you can do it.
بأي طريقة تستطيعون
And if you don't know how, please find me -- I will help you.
واذا لم تعرفوا الكيفية، الرجاء البحث عني. سأساعدكم
Last but not least, Bill Gates, I know you invented Windows.
أخيراً وليس آخراً، بيل قيتس، أعرف أنك اخترعت ويندوس
Wait till you see, maybe next year, what kind of windows we've invented.
أنتظر لترى، ربما العام المقبل، أي نوع من الويندوس أخترعناه نحن
Thank you so much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)